

WIRELESS SYSTEMS PHD CANDIDATE · EMBEDDED SOFTWARE ENGINEER

209 N 9th Street, Apt. 3B, Philadelphia, PA 19107, USA

□ (+1) 408-772-0602 | ■ danh@dnguyen.io | 🕏 www.dnguyen.io | 🖸 dnguyen85 | 🛅 dnguyen85

Summary.

PhD candidate with 7 years' experience in research and development of hardware, software, and system components for modern wireless communication systems. Fluent in embedded / FPGA development, digital signal processing, C, Python, and Matlab. Currently seeking full-time opportunities in the general areas of mobile computing and wireless PHY/MAC development.

Education

Drexel UniversityPhiladelphia, PA

PH.D. IN ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING (ADVISORS: K. R. DANDEKAR, N. KANDASAMY)

2009-Exp. 6/2017

Thesis: "Agile Spectrum Sharing Wireless Systems using Software Defined Radios and Reconfigurable Antennas"

Drexel UniversityPhiladelphia, PA

M.S. IN COMPUTER ENGINEERING

2009–2014

Hands-on experience in **computer architecture**, **hardware/software co-design**, and **telecommunications**

Drexel UniversityPhiladelphia, PA

B.S. IN COMPUTER ENGINEERING

2006–2009

Graduated Summa Cum Laude, GPA: 3.96

Skills_

Programming C / Python / Matlab (proficient), Java / C++ (intermediate), HTML / CSS, Javascript

Libraries NumPy / Pandas (Python), GNU Radio / Intel IPP (C++), lwIP / liquid-dsp (C), CUDA / OpenCL (GPGPU)

Hardware Xilinx & Altera FPGA platforms, VHDL, Verilog, Xilinx ISE, Modelsim, JTAG debugging

Architectures x86, x86-64, ARM, Xilinx Microblaze, Atmel AVR microcontrollers

Operating Systems Unix / Linux, OpenWRT / FreeRTOS (embedded), TinyOS / Contiki (wireless sensors)

Wireless Standards IEEE 802.11n/ac/ad (WiFi), 802.15.4 (ZigBee), Bluetooth, GSM, UMTS/W-CDMA, LTE, MIMO, mmWave **RF Test Equipment** Network analyzer, vector signal generator, channel emulator, anechoic / reverberation chamber

Others Vim, Tmux, shell scripting, Git, Latex, Markdown, Pandoc, Inkscape

Experience

Drexel Wireless System Laboratory

Philadelphia, PA

GRADUATE RESEARCH FELLOW

9/2009-Present

- Designed and implemented a **synchronous directional wireless architecture** that leverages time synchronization and dynamic antenna directionality to perform autonomous, machine learning-based beamsteering for optimizing network throughput. Built a real-time 802.11 system prototype on the WARP software-defined radio. Three publications [3,4; W1]
- Developed an **FPGA-based software-defined radio testbed** for dynamic spectrum access research in wireless small cells, leveraging a frequency-agile transceiver frontend for flexible spectrum operations. One publication [8]
- Implemented a **real-time**, **protocol-aware reactive jammer** using GNU Radio and the low-cost USRP N210 software radio platform. Three publications [9,10,12] and a patent [P1]
- Co-developed a **reconfigurable baseband hardware IP** for scalable ultra wide-band OFDM signaling at millimeter wave (mmWave) frequencies. Implemented VHDL RTL modules to interface the baseband pipeline with high-speed (1GSPS) ADC and DAC frontends. Verified hardware designs in Modelsim and Xilinx Chipscope. Two publications [11,13]
- Investigated **automatic generation of software components** for physical layer processing. Extended SPIRAL—a code generator for DSP transforms (http://spiral.net)—to handle baseband processing kernels. Developed algorithmic break-down rules to enable Spiral to generate optimized C implementations of the baseband pipeline on x86 platforms
- Handled backend development (cloud-controlled radios, gateway, and server software) of a **mobile augmented reality** framework to visualize and control RF transmissions in wireless networks in real time. See [2,5,7] for publications. Demo video: http://beamviewer.io
- Developed and maintained the lab website at http://wireless.ece.drexel.edu

InterDigital Communications, Inc.

King of Prussia, PA

RESEARCH INTERN - VIDEO OVER WIRELESS

6/2013-6/2014

- Prototyped an experimental WiFi video delivery system using OpenWRT with modified Linux 802.11 drivers (mac80211 and n180211 modules), and DASH (Dynamic Adaptive Streaming over HTTP) video clients
- Optimized H.264 video streaming over WiFi networks leveraging IEEE 802.11e QoS support for traffic access categories
- Implemented a control algorithm for network-assisted rebuffering prevention through OoS elevation of distressed video streams

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Drexel University

Philadelphia, PA

TEACHING ASSISTANT

2009-2014

· Taught lectures and led lab sessions on Matlab, digital logic design, Java programming, and embedded systems

Freedom Rings Partnership

Philadelphia, PA

WEB DEVELOPER

8/2012-8/2013

Developed in Drupal CMS key features for the Freedom Rings Partnership's KEYSPOT website (https://www.phillykeyspots.org)

MediaTech, Inc. (Vietnam)

Hanoi, Vietnam

TECHNICAL CONSULTANT

1-5/2012

- Designed and implemented a proof-of-concept PBX phone system for live-broadcast TV interactive games based on Asterisk
- Performed system latency tests using landline, cellular, and SIP-based soft phones

Drexel High Performance Computing Laboratory

Philadelphia, PA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT (ADVISOR: J. JOHNSON)

6-12/2009

- Investigated performance bottlenecks of static auto-tuning software for sparse matrix-vector multiplication on x86 CPU platforms
- Analyzed and tested a lab-built Multiply-Accumulate (MAC) hardware design on FPGA using Xilinx ISE Suite

Motorola Inc. - Home & Network Mobility Division (now ARRIS Group, Inc.)

Horsham, PA

SOFTWARE ENGINEER CO-OP

3/2008-6/2009

- Developed C++ features for the thin client software layer of set-top boxes to enhance digital video recording (DVR). Debugged and improved device drivers for external mass storage devices (eMSD) to handle DVR's external hard drive configuration process
- Implemented the System Test Program (STP) framework for automation of all design validation tests in the group

SAP America, Inc.

Newtown Square, PA

R/3 SYSTEM ADMINISTRATOR CO-OP

3-9/2007

Provided R/3 basis technical support for SAP systems used for demo, training, and consulting purposes

Publications

CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

- [1] Enhancing Blind Interference Alignment with Reinforcement Learning S. Begashaw, D. H. Nguyen, K. R. Dandekar Proc. of IEEE Global Communications Conf. (GLOBECOM '16 - to appear), 2016
- [2] Demo: WiART Visualize and Interact with Wireless Networks using Augmented Reality
 D. H. Nguyen, J. Chacko, L. Henderson, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar
 Proc. of 22nd Annu. Intl. Conf. on Mobile Computing and Networking (ACM MobiCom '16), 2016
- [3] Enabling Synchronous Directional Channel Access on SDRs for Spectrum Sharing Applications
 D. H. Nguyen, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar
 Proc. of ACM Intl. Workshop on Wireless Network Testbeds, Experimental Eval., and Characterization (WiNTECH '16), 2016
- [4] Demo: Enhancing Indoor Spatial Reuse through Adaptive Antenna Beamsteering (WinCool Best Demo Award)
 D. H. Nguyen, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar
 Proc. of ACM Intl. Workshop on Wireless Network Testbeds, Experimental Eval., and Characterization (WiNTECH '16), 2016
- [5] BeamViewer: Visualization of Dynamic Antenna Radiation Patterns using Augmented Reality
 D. H. Nguyen, L. Henderson, J. Chacko, C. Sahin, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar
 Proc. of IEEE Conf. on Computer Communications Workshops (INFOCOM WKSHPS '16), 2016
- [6] Experimental Evaluation of a Reconfigurable Antenna System for Blind Interference Alignment S. Begashaw, J. Chacko, N. Gulati, D. H. Nguyen, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of IEEE Wireless and Microwave Technology Conf. (WAMICON '16*), 2016

- [7] Wireless Communications Engineering and Cybersecurity Education via Augmented Reality C. Sahin, D. H. Nguyen, S. Begashaw, B. Katz, J. Chacko, L. Henderson, J. Stanford, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of IEEE Frontiers in Education Conf. (FIE '16)*, 2016
- [8] Leveraging an Agile RF Transceiver for Rapid Prototyping of Small-Cell Systems D. H. Nguyen, M. Rauhanummi, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of IEEE Vehicular Technology Conf. (VTC-Fall '15)*, 2015
- [9] Wireless Cybersecurity Education via a Software Defined Radio Laboratory C. Sahin, D. Nguyen, J. Chacko, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of IEEE Frontiers in Education Conf. (FIE '15)*, 2015
- [10] A Real-Time and Protocol-Aware Reactive Jamming Framework Built on Software-Defined Radios D. Nguyen, C. Sahin, B. Shishkin, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar Proc. of ACM Workshop on Software Radio Implementation Forum (SRIF '14), 2014
- [11] FPGA-Based Latency-Insensitive OFDM Pipeline for Wireless Research J. Chacko, C. Sahin, D. Nguyen, D. Pfeil, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of IEEE High Performance Extreme Computing Conf. (HPEC '14)*, 2014
- [12] Real-Time, Channel-Aware Reactive Jamming in 802.11 Networks D. Nguyen, B. Shishkin, C. Sahin, D. Dorsey, N. Kandasamy, K. Dandekar *Proc. of 2013 Wireless @ Virginia Tech Annu. Symp.* 2013
- [13] SDC Testbed: Software Defined Communications Testbed for Wireless Radio and Optical Networking
 B. Shishkin, D. Pfeil, D. Nguyen, K. Wanuga, J. Chacko, J. Johnson, N. Kandasamy, T. P. Kurzweg, K. R. Dandekar
 Proc. of Intl. Symp. on Modeling and Optimization in Mobile, Ad Hoc, and Wireless Networks (WiOPT '11), 2011

WORKING PAPERS (Unpublished)

[W1] LinkPursuit: An Adaptive Pursuit Learning Method to Mitigate Small-Cell Interference through Directionality D. H. Nguyen, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar Submitted (unsuccessfully) to ACM MobiCom '16. Under revision, 2016

PATENT / PATENT APPLICATIONS

- [P1] Real-Time, Channel-Aware Reactive Jamming in Wireless Networks
 B. Shishkin, D. H. Nguyen, C. Sahin, K. R. Dandekar, N. Kandasamy, D. J. Dorsey
 US Patent No. 9,531,497. Issued December 27, 2016
- [P2] Beam Visualization and STEM Education using Augmented Reality
 K. R. Dandekar, C. Sahin, L. J. Henderson, D. H. Nguyen, J. J. Chacko, X. R. Rey
 US Provisional Patent Application No. 62/403,415. Filed October 3, 2016
- [P3] An Adaptive Pursuit Learning Method to Mitigate Small-Cell Interference through Directionality D. H. Nguyen, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar US Provisional Patent Application No. 62/402,671. Filed September 30, 2016

Honors & Awards

WinCool Best Demo, ACM WiNTECH '16 (judged by a panel from industry and academia)
 2009-Present
 Graduate Research Fellow, Drexel University
 Milton Rosenberg Scholar, Drexel University (recognizing outstanding engineering students)
 Senior Design Competition Winner, Drexel ECE (for a real-time RFID-based product locating system)
 Dean's Scholarship Recipient, Drexel University
 Inductee, Eta Kappa Nu National ECE Honor Society

Academic Projects

NACHOS EDUCATIONAL OPERATING SYSTEM IMPLEMENTATION

Fall 2011

• Implemented in Java various features of a modern operating system: paging, virtual memory, locks and semaphores, conditional variables, and multi-threaded operations

FAST FOURIER TRANSFORM (FFT) PERFORMANCE BENCHMARKING ON CPU AND GPU

Winter 2011

3

• Implemented and measured runtime performance of various FFT implementation in C and CUDA

 Wrote C programs to perform LU decomposition on large matrices, then parallelized the implementations using Pthreads, OpenMP. and Cilk

COMPILER CONSTRUCTION FOR SPL (SIGNAL PROCESSING LANGUAGE)

Spring 2010

 Constructed a scanner, parser, and interpreter for a Lisp-style language targeted for describing signal processing kernels called SPL, using Java Lex and Yacc

IMPLEMENTATION OF A 5-STAGE PIPELINED CPU ON FPGA

Winter 2010

• Implemented a 5-stage pipelined CPU supporting Load/Store, R-type instructions, branching, and context switches in VHDL. Performed FPGA synthesis and verification on the Xilinx Spartan 3E board

Other Activities

Journal and Conference Peer-Review

Philadelphia, PA

EXTERNAL REVIEWER

2012-Present

Performed peer-review and provided publication recommendations for submitted manuscripts

National Science Foundation (NSF) Research Grant Proposals

Drexel University

CONTRIBUTOR

2011-Present

• Performed literature survey, formulated research thrusts, and assisted the Principal Investigators (PIs) in writing grant proposals

Local Political Convention (Democratic National Convention)

Philadelphia, PA

RADIO FREQUENCY (RF) COORDINATION VOLUNTEER

7/2016

· Handled the RF coordination procedure: static allocation of available spectrum to media organizations, device inspection and tagging, floor sweep to monitor spectrum usage, troubleshoot interference incidents

IEEE Student Branch Drexel University

LOGISTICS CHAIR

2010

2008

· Handled logistics operations in the organization: organize membership drives, book event venues, prepare refreshments and meeting materials, contact and schedule event speakers

GSA Education, Inc. Hanoi, Vietnam

FOUNDING MEMBER

Co-founded a professional education service company in Vietnam. Services include tutoring and college application consulting

• Led the development of the company's web portal for customer relationship management